Hello everyone and welcome to another lesson here at EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听另一节EnglishPod课程。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
And I'm Catherine and today we have an elementary level lesson all about life with a roommate.
我是Catherine，今天我们有一节初级课程，内容是关于和室友一起生活的方方面面。
That's right.
没错。
So sometimes during college you have to live with a roommate because living alone is too
所以有时候在大学期间，你得和室友一起住，因为独自生活太
expensive.
贵了。
Also, after college I know that a lot of people who are just starting their jobs often live
而且，我知道很多刚毕业开始工作的人，也经常
with a roommate to save some money.
和室友一起住来省钱。
That's right.
没错。
Or maybe your girlfriend could be considered kind of like your romantic roommate.
或者你的女朋友也可以被看作是一种浪漫的室友。
I hope not in the sense of today's lesson.
希望不是今天这节课里那种感觉。
We're talking about problems with a roommate.
我们讲的是和室友之间的问题。
So let's listen to this dialogue and we'll be back in a moment.
那我们来听听这段对话，一会儿再回来。
Charlie, do you have a second?
Charlie，你有空吗？
Yeah, what's up?
嗯，怎么了？
Well, I went and paid the bills today and you still haven't given me your half.
呃，我今天去付了账单，你还没给我你那份钱。
Yeah, I wanted to talk to you about that.
是啊，我正想跟你谈谈这事。
I agreed we would go halves on all the bills, but frankly I think it's unfair.
我同意过我们平摊所有账单，但老实说，我觉得这不公平。
Unfair?
不公平？
Why?
为什么？
Well, you have long hair and use the hair dryer every morning.
嗯，你头发长，每天早上都用吹风机。
I don't.
我不用。
You leave your computer on all night downloading torrents.
你整晚开着电脑下载种子文件。
I don't.
我不下载。
You see what I'm getting at here?
你明白我的意思吗？
You leave the air conditioner on day and night.
你白天黑夜都开着空调。
You also take 30 minute showers, which means you're using way more gas and water than me.
你还每次洗澡洗30分钟，这意味着你用的煤气和水比我多得多。
Well, while we're on the subject, stop bringing your friends over for drinks every weekend.
好吧，既然说到这个，你别每个周末都带朋友来喝酒了。
You always leave a mess and keep me up all night.
你总是弄得一团糟，还吵得我一整晚睡不着。
Maybe you should just move out and find another place.
也许你该搬出去，另找个地方住。
Maybe you should move out.
也许你才该搬出去。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So we have a couple of different words that we're going to take a look at now in Language
现在我们要看几个不同的单词，在“语言
Takeaway.
小贴士”环节。
Language Takeaway.
语言小贴士。
So the first word is a dreaded word that means that most people don't like it.
第一个词是个让人头疼的词，意思是大多数人都不喜欢它。
They fear it.
他们害怕它。
This is bills.
这个词是“bills”（账单）。
That's right.
没错。
You have to pay your bills.
你得付账单。
So a bill is the paper that tells you how much you have to pay.
所以账单就是告诉你需要付多少钱的那张纸。
That's right.
没错。
So you can have a gas bill.
所以你可以有煤气账单。
An electricity bill.
电费账单。
A cable bill.
有线电视账单。
Or even at the restaurant, you ask for the bill.
甚至在餐厅里，你会要账单。
All right, so this is the amount of money you need to pay.
好的，所以这就是你需要付的金额。
That's right.
没错。
And usually at the end of the month, you receive many, many bills in the mail and you have
而且通常在月底，你会收到很多很多账单邮件，你得
to pay the companies like the gas company and the electricity company.
付钱给那些公司，比如煤气公司和电力公司。
That's right.
没错。
So those are bills.
所以那些就是账单。
A singular would be a bill.
单数形式是“a bill”。
And so this is how the argument starts.
这就是争吵的起因。
The two roommates decide that they have to pay the bills, but they don't want to split
两个室友决定要付账单，但他们不想
the bills in half, go halves.
平摊账单，也就是“go halves”。
They have to pay their own.
他们得付自己的那份。
And so one person says, listen, this isn't fair.
所以有个人说，听着，这不公平。
You leave your computer on all night downloading torrents.
你整晚开着电脑下载种子文件。
Okay, so we understand what it is to download something or you download this podcast, but
好的，我们明白下载东西是什么意思，或者你下载这个播客，但
a torrent, what is that?
“torrent”（种子文件）是什么？
That's kind of technical.
这有点技术性。
That is.
是的。
So a torrent is a kind of file that you can download from the internet.
所以种子文件是一种可以从互联网上下载的文件。
So basically when you want to download a movie or some music from the internet, you go to
基本上，当你想从网上下载一部电影或一些音乐时，你去一个
a website that will connect you to someone who owns this movie or book or music and they'll
网站，它会把你连接到拥有这部电影、书或音乐的人，他们会有
have a special file that's called a torrent file and that's what you download.
一个特殊的文件，叫做种子文件，那就是你下载的东西。
That's right.
没错。
So it's a new way of downloading files off the internet from many people, kind of like
所以这是一种从互联网上从很多人那里下载文件的新方式，有点像
a peer sharing.
点对点分享。
That's right.
没错。
So when one person disappears or goes offline, it shares you with another person.
所以当一个人消失或下线时，它会把你连接到另一个人。
That's right.
没错。
So those are torrents.
所以那些就是种子文件。
And now, well, they kept arguing about you have to pay this, I have to pay that.
现在，嗯，他们继续争吵，你要付这个，我要付那个。
So you said, you know what, you should just move out.
所以你说，你知道吗，你该搬出去。
Ooh, so to move out, this is a phrase that has two words to move out.
哦，所以“move out”（搬出去），这是一个由两个词组成的短语。
It means to leave this house forever, this apartment.
意思是永远离开这个房子、这个公寓。
So that means to find a new place to live.
也就是说要找一个新的地方住。
Right.
对。
So I can say, oh, I'm moving out this weekend.
所以我可以这么说，哦，我这周末要搬出去了。
That means I'm changing apartments.
意思是我要换公寓了。
Right.
对。
Or my boyfriend just moved out.
或者我男朋友刚搬走了。
Okay.
好的。
That's really sad.
那真让人难过。
He left your house.
他离开了你的房子。
Okay.
好的。
So that is to move out.
所以这就是“搬出去”的意思。
And now we have a word that is more colloquial of how to say a house or an apartment.
现在我们有一个更口语化的词，用来表示房子或公寓。
This is place.
就是“地方”。
Okay.
好的。
So you just say a place.
所以你就说“一个地方”。
So place normally is a location.
“地方”通常指一个位置。
Okay.
好的。
Where is this place?
这个地方在哪儿？
But we could say, hey, we're going to have dinner at my place.
但我们可以说，嘿，我们要在我家吃晚饭。
Would you like to come?
你想来吗？
So that means we're going to have dinner at my house.
意思就是我们要在我家吃晚饭。
Right.
对。
My place, his place.
我家，他家。
His place.
他家。
Or you have a really nice place.
或者你有个很不错的房子。
Thanks.
谢谢。
Okay.
好的。
So that means you have a really nice house.
所以那意味着你有个很不错的房子。
Exactly.
没错。
Okay.
好的。
So four key words today when we listen to the dialogue again and we'll be back in a
所以今天有四个关键词，当我们再听一遍对话时，我们一会儿
little bit.
就回来。
Charlie, do you have a second?
查理，你有空吗？
Yeah, what's up?
嗯，怎么了？
Well, I went and paid the bills today and you still haven't given me your half.
呃，我今天去付了账单，你还没给我你那一半。
Yeah, I wanted to talk to you about that.
嗯，我正想跟你谈谈这事。
I agreed we would go halves on all the bills, but frankly, I think it's unfair.
我同意我们平摊所有账单，但老实说，我觉得这不公平。
Unfair?
不公平？
Why?
为什么？
Well, you have long hair and use the hairdryer every morning.
呃，你头发长，每天早上都用吹风机。
I don't.
我不用。
You leave your computer on all night downloading torrents.
你整晚开着电脑下载种子。
I don't.
我不这么认为。
You see what I'm getting at here?
你明白我的意思吗？
You leave the air conditioner on day and night.
你白天黑夜都开着空调。
You also take 30 minute showers, which means you're using way more gas and water than me.
你还洗30分钟的澡，这意味着你用的煤气和水比我多得多。
Well, while we're on the subject, stop bringing your friends over for drinks every weekend.
好吧，既然说到这个，别每个周末都带朋友来喝酒了。
You always leave a mess and keep me up all night.
你总是弄得一团糟，还让我整晚睡不着。
Maybe you should just move out and find another place.
也许你应该搬出去，另找个地方住。
Maybe you should move out.
也许你才该搬出去。
All right, we are back and we've got some great phrases today coming up in Fluency Builders.
好了，我们回来了，今天的“流利度训练”里有一些很棒的短语。
Let's take a look at some of those.
我们来看看其中一些。
Fluency Builder.
流利度训练。
All right, so the first phrase that we have, very common, very, very common, but also
好的，第一个短语，非常常见，非常非常常见，但对英语学习者来说
very difficult for English learners to answer this question.
回答这个问题却很难。
All right, what's up?
好的，怎么了？
What's up?
怎么了？
So if somebody says, what's up, what does that mean?
如果有人问“怎么了”，那是什么意思？
That means what's going on?
意思是“发生什么事了？”
What's new?
“有什么新鲜事？”
How are you?
“你好吗？”
How is it going?
“最近怎么样？”
Okay.
好的。
Hi.
嗨。
So how should you answer this?
那么你应该怎么回答这个问题呢？
Okay, so think of what's up as being a question about what's new, what's happening.
好的，所以把“what's up”想成是在问有什么新鲜事、发生了什么。
You can say, what's up?
你可以说，“what's up？”
Oh, not much.
哦，没什么。
Not much.
没什么。
Okay, what's up means what's new?
好的，“what's up”意思是有什么新鲜事吗？
Oh, not much is new.
哦，没什么新鲜事。
Not much.
没什么。
Everything is the same.
一切都一样。
So what's up?
那么“what's up”呢？
You could say, hey, hi, how are you?
你可以说，“嘿，嗨，你好吗？”
It's another way to say hi.
这是另一种打招呼的方式。
Okay.
好的。
But you can't say, this guy.
但你不能说，“这家伙。”
Right, or sometimes English learners will say, fine, thank you, because they think that
对，或者有时候英语学习者会说，“很好，谢谢”，因为他们认为
what's up means how are you?
“what's up”意思是“你好吗？”
No, that's different.
不，那不一样。
So you cannot say, fine, thank you, fine, well.
所以你不能说，“很好，谢谢，很好，不错。”
These are words that answer how are you questions, but this isn't a how are you question.
这些是回答“你好吗”这类问题的词，但这不是一个“你好吗”的问题。
This is a what's new question.
这是一个“有什么新鲜事”的问题。
What's new or hi.
“有什么新鲜事”或“嗨”。
Okay, so somebody says, what's up?
好的，所以有人说，“怎么了？”
You can say, not much, or you can say, hey, what's up?
你可以说，“没什么”，或者说，“嘿，怎么了？”
You can say, what's up back?
你可以反问，“怎么了？”
What's up?
怎么了？
What's up with you?
你怎么样？
Yeah, what's up with you?
是啊，你怎么样？
Okay, so that's our first phrase.
好的，这就是我们的第一个短语。
Now, when the guy was talking about the hair dryer and the computer, he finished off that
现在，当那个人谈到吹风机和电脑时，他结束了那段话
paragraph by saying, you see what I'm getting at here?
说，“你明白我的意思吗？”
Okay, you're doing this.
好的，你在做这个。
You use the hair dryer, you leave the computer on.
你用吹风机，让电脑开着。
Do you see what I'm getting at here?
你明白我的意思吗？
First phrase, do you see what I'm getting at?
第一个短语，“你明白我的意思吗？”
It means, do you understand what I'm talking about?
它的意思是，“你明白我在说什么吗？”
Do you see my point?
你明白我的观点吗？
That means I haven't said exactly what I mean, but you should understand what I'm saying.
这意味着我没有直接说出我的意思，但你应该理解我在说什么。
So he's saying, you're wasting electricity.
所以他在说，“你在浪费电。”
You use all of these services more than I do.
你用的这些服务比我多得多。
And we could say, maybe Marco didn't get a good grade in his English test last week.
我们可以说，也许马可上周英语考试没考好。
I say, listen, maybe it has to do with your study habits or how much you love video games
我说，听着，这可能跟你的学习习惯或者你有多爱玩电子游戏有关。
or how little time you spend at school.
或者你在学校待的时间有多短。
Do you see what I'm getting at?
你明白我的意思吗？
Okay, so you're not saying directly that I don't study.
好吧，所以你并没有直接说我不学习。
You're just telling me the reasons, maybe why as to why I'm not studying.
你只是在告诉我原因，也许是我为什么不学习的原因。
Like a hint.
就像在暗示。
Okay, so that's what you say when you don't tell somebody directly what the problem is.
好的，这就是当你没有直接告诉别人问题是什么时说的话。
You say, you see what I'm getting at here?
你说，你明白我的意思吗？
Do you see what I'm getting at?
你明白我的意思吗？
Getting at means hinting.
“Getting at”意思是暗示。
Okay, and our last phrase, when they kept talking about the bills, one of the person
好的，我们最后一个短语，当他们一直在谈论账单时，其中一个人
said, you are using way more gas and water than me.
说，你用的煤气和水比我多得多。
So what about this way more?
那这个“way more”是什么意思？
Way more.
多得多。
Way means much or a lot.
“Way”意思是“非常”或“很多”。
So we could say, you are using a lot more water than I am.
所以我们可以说，你用的水比我多得多。
Or you're using way more water.
或者你用的水多得多。
This is very spoken language.
这是非常口语化的表达。
This is not written language.
这不是书面语言。
So don't write this down on your tests.
所以别在考试里写这个。
But way more means a lot more, much more.
但“way more”意思是“多得多”、“多很多”。
Okay, you can say, Bob is way more attractive than Bill.
好，你可以说：鲍勃比比尔有魅力得多。
That's right.
没错。
Or this is way more interesting than that show.
或者：这比那个节目有趣得多。
Okay, so you can say way more instead of much more or a lot more, but it's usually spoken
好，所以你可以用“way more”代替“much more”或“a lot more”，但这通常是口语
English.
英语。
Exactly.
正是。
All right, let's listen to our dialogue for the last time and we'll be back in a bit to
好了，让我们最后一次听对话，一会儿回来再
talk a little bit more.
多聊一点。
Charlie, do you have a second?
查理，你有空吗？
Yeah, what's up?
有，怎么了？
Well, I went and paid the bills today and you still haven't given me your half.
嗯，我今天去付了账单，你还没给我你那一半。
Yeah, I wanted to talk to you about that.
是啊，我正想跟你谈谈这事。
I agreed we would go halves on all the bills, but frankly, I think it's unfair.
我同意过我们平摊所有账单，但老实说，我觉得这不公平。
Unfair?
不公平？
Why?
为什么？
Well, you have long hair and use the hairdryer every morning.
嗯，你留长头发，每天早上用吹风机。
I don't.
我不用。
You leave your computer on all night downloading torrents.
你整晚开着电脑下载种子文件。
I don't.
我没有。
You see what I'm getting at here?
你明白我的意思吗？
You leave the air conditioner on day and night.
你白天黑夜都开着空调。
You also take 30 minute showers, which means you're using way more gas and water than me.
你还洗30分钟的澡，这意味着你用的燃气和水比我多得多。
Well, while we're on the subject, stop bringing your friends over for drinks every weekend.
好吧，既然说到这个，别每个周末都带朋友来喝酒了。
You always leave a mess and keep me up all night.
你总是弄得一团糟，还让我整晚睡不着。
Maybe you should just move out and find another place.
也许你该搬出去，另找个地方住。
Maybe you should move out.
也许你该搬出去。
So Marco, have you ever had any of these problems with a roommate?
那么马可，你和室友有过这些问题吗？
I've actually stayed away from roommates because of issues like this.
我其实因为这类问题一直避免和室友同住。
You mean you have not had many roommates because you're afraid of this situation?
你是说你没怎么有过室友，是因为害怕这种情况？
Yeah, I've always actually tried to live on my own by myself, like in a small apartment
是的，我一直尽量自己住，比如住个小公寓。
or studio, or if I have to have a roommate, maybe just one, not a house full of roommates.
或者单间公寓，如果必须合租，可能就一个人，而不是一屋子室友。
Because I think the more people there are, the little bit more complicated it gets.
因为我觉得人越多，事情就越复杂。
And if it's just two, it's a little bit simpler.
如果只有两个人，就简单一些。
This is true, although sometimes I think it depends on the people that you're sharing
这倒是真的，不过有时候我觉得这取决于和你合住的人。
a house with.
取决于和你合住的人。
I've had one awkward experience where people did not want to pay ever, and they were always
我有过一次尴尬的经历，有人总是不想付钱，而且总是拖欠付款。
late with their payments, and one situation where people were very good about it, so always
还有一次情况是大家都很守规矩，所以总是很顺利。
remembered and were very helpful.
他们记得并且非常有帮助。
So it really depends.
所以这真的要看情况。
Yeah, I think it's hard to live with someone always, of course.
是啊，我觉得和某人一直住在一起当然很难。
Even if you start living with your girlfriend or boyfriend or you get married, it's kind
即使你开始和女朋友或男朋友同居，或者结婚，和另一个人住在一起
of different to live with someone.
还是有点不同的。
And especially money-wise, I think it always complicates things with people.
尤其是在钱的问题上，我觉得这总是会让事情变得复杂。
Definitely.
确实如此。
So I think you're right, though.
不过我觉得你说得对。
If there's two people, it's very easy to share the bills.
如果是两个人，分摊账单很容易。
But if there's five people or six people, it's very hard to find out who spent more
但如果是五个人或六个人，就很难弄清楚谁花了更多
money or what the rules are.
钱，或者规则是什么。
Yeah, so it can get a little bit complicated.
是啊，所以可能会变得有点复杂。
But I'm sure a lot of our listeners have probably had roommates before, maybe in college, maybe
但我相信很多听众可能以前有过室友，也许在大学里，也许
even now.
甚至现在。
So let's hear those experiences and maybe those good and bad stories about living with
所以让我们听听那些经历，以及那些关于和别人住在一起的
other people.
好故事和坏故事。
So please get in touch with us.
所以请与我们联系。
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
我们的网站是 EnglishPod.com。
There's lots of places for you to ask questions and to post your own experiences with roommates.
那里有很多地方可以让你提问，并分享你与室友的经历。
We hope to see you there, and until next time.
我们希望能在那里见到你，下次再见。
Bye.
再见。
Thank you very much.
非常感谢。